Guide to the National Council on Religion and Public Education Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
National Council on Religion and Public Education Records
1971-1994
RG 262
Yale University Divinity School Library
13
(26 boxes)
These archives present the best collection of materials in the United States on the subject of Religion and Public Education. Not only do they contain the records of the National Council on Religion and Public Education, 1971-1994, but of other parallel organizations in the field, such as the National Council of Churches, the National Conference of Christians and Jews, and the Public Education Religion Studies Center of Wright State University. Included in the archives are the papers of the Rev. Richard U. Smith, an Episcopal priest, who was a pioneer in the field of weekday religious education and the first director of the NCRPE. The Religious Education Association took the leadership in organizing the NCRPE in 1971, but it was incorporated as a separate non-profit organization in 1973 under the laws of the state of New York.
National Council on Religion and Public Education (U.S.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Religious Education Association, 2014
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
In 1962 the U.S. Supreme Court ruled, in the case of Engel v. Vitale, that a prayer written by the New York State Board of Regents for use in schools was unconstitutional. The following year the high court declared, in two cases coming out of Pennsylvania and Maryland, that the reading of the Bible and the Lord's Prayer in public schools were also unconstitutional. There were many efforts to amend the Constitution to permit prayer, and a number of organizations, institutions, pronouncements, and publications sought to respond to the decision, especially the dicta from Justice Tom Clark that the decision did not prohibit the objective study of religion as a part of a secular program of education.
Late in 1970 J. Blaine Fister of the National Council of Churches convened a meeting of representatives of the different organizations that were dealing with the subject, and he asked Boardman Kathan of the Religious Education Association to take the leadership in planning a larger consultation. A survey showed that the three issues that needed to be addressed were: curriculum development, teacher training and public awareness. A consultation was held on April 27, 1971, at the headquarters of the National Conference of Christians and Jews, and was attended by 25 leaders. Presiding, besides Kathan, was Bernhard Olson of the NCCJ. Fister presented a background paper, and the main speaker was John Whitney, director of the Pennsylvania Religious Literature Course. The group voted to form a national coalition.
Plans were made for a two-day conference at the Statler-Hilton in New York City on Nov. 30-Dec. 1, 1971. Kathan wrote a grant proposal and the W. Clement and Jessie V. Stone Foundation awarded a total of $9,000 to the Religious Education Association. The R.E.A. added $5,400 to the project, along with a $3,000 "staff expansion fund," that was received from St. Thomas Church in New York City. Richard U. Smith, an Episcopalian priest, was hired as the director of the project. Sixty people from over 40 organizations attended the conference. Three major addresses were featured in the Religious News Service: Philip Phenix of Columbia University Teacher's College; Rabbi Arthur Gilbert, author of The Reader's Bible; and Fr. William Tobin of the U.S. Catholic Conference. The group voted to form the National Council on Religion and Public Education. Kathan continued as Chairman of the Steering Committee, and Olson as Vice-chairman.
Grants from the Cleveland H. Dodge Foundation and the General Service Foundation made it possible to publish the proceedings of the conference, edited by Smith, as Part 2 of the July-August 1972 issue of the journal, Religious Education. Included in the volume was a section on "Teacher Education and Curriculum Development," with reports from Pennsylvania, Florida, Nebraska, California, Ohio, Indiana, Massachusetts, and Michigan. There was a list of suggested organizations to contact for further information and a Bibliography prepared by James V. Panoch of the Religious Instruction Association.
The first annual meeting of the NCRPE was held in 1972 at the Palmer House in Chicago and was attended by 120 persons. Delivering major addresses were Robert Michaelsen of the University of California, Santa Barbara, and John Whitney of Penn State University. Neil McCluskey succeeded Kathan as Chairman of the Steering Committee. Whitney recommended that the NCRPE become incorporated as a separate organization, rather than continue as a project of the R.E.A., and that the Steering Committee become a Board of Directors. This was done in 1953 under the laws of the state of New York. McCluskey was elected President and Smith continued as Executive Director until 1975.
Annual meetings were held, providing a forum and establishing a network of people involved in teacher training and curriculum development. In some years meetings were held with the National Council of Social Studies, the American Academy of Religion and other organizations. James Kirkpatrick of the American Association of School Administrators was an active member. An outstanding example of networking was the promotion of a world religions course developed by Wes Bodin and Lee Smith, two teachers in St. Louis Park, Minnesota. Another example were the training courses at Indiana University taught by James Ackerman and Thayer Warshaw. Executive Directors who followed Smith were Nancy Fuchs as interim, Daryl Adrian of Ball State University, with Walter Horlander of the Indiana Council of Churches as his associate, Lynn Taylor of the University of Kansas, and Gerrit tenZythoff of Southwestern Missouri State University. Others who served as President were J. Blaine Fister of the NCC, James Wood of Baylor University, Wes Bodin, Nicholas Piediscalzi of Wright State University, Charles Haynes of George Mason University, and Austin Creel of the University of Florida.
A major accomplishment was the official publication of the Council. It started out in 1974 as a four-page newsletter, NCRPE Bulletin, edited by Donald Wimmer of Seton Hall University. By Spring 1976 it had become a 16-page booklet. From 1979 to 1982 it was edited by Thayer Warshaw, who had been a teacher at Newton North High School in Massachusett. Charles Kniker of Iowa State University took over as editor of the bulletin in 1983, but the following year the name of the journal was changed to Religion and Public Education, and included book reviews, curriculum and poetry in addition to news. In 1993 Charles Russo became editor-in-chief and the enterprise was moved to Webster University, St. Louis. After 1994 the journal was named Religion and Education.
The NCRPE distributed handbooks, lesson plans and other materials written or edited by Thayer Warshaw on the Bible as literature. One example was "Reviews of Curricular and Resource Materials." Another was The Bible in Literature Course: Successful Lesson Plans, edited by Linda Meixner, an English teacher in Parma, Ohio. Under the leadership of Charles Haynes, the NCRPE distributed thousands of flyers with Questions and Answers on "Religious Holidays in the Public Schools" "Religion in the Public School Curriculum," and "The Equal Access Act and the Public Schools." A distribution center was set up at Iowa State University and was later moved to the Indiana University of Pennsylvania. There was an attempt at a newsletter in the early 1990s, with the help of the Association of Supervision and Curriculum Development.
The NCRPE came to an end in 1994 because of a number of things: a dwindling number of organizational members; inadequate financial support; the parallel existence of the Public Education Religious Studies Center at Wright State University with generous funding and staff; energy and interest absorbed by a section of he American Academy of Religion; and the "disconnect" between similar studies in higher education and the world of tax-supported public schools. There was also the feeling that the NCRPE had accomplished its goals. Besides the renamed journal, the NCRPE left a distribution center at the University of California at Chico. The NCRPE had also provided advice and assistance to hundreds of school districts and thousands of teachers who wanted to provide their students with a "constitutionally sound" and "educationally appropriate" curriculum on teaching about religion. Charles Haynes has pointed out that after 1994 there have been other coalition efforts, even broader than those in the NCRPE era, that have found "common ground," issued joint statements, and guidelines, and averted much controversy.
Scope and Contents
The Archives of the National Council on Religion and Public Education consist of 250 files, plus 30 issues of the journal, Religion and Public Education, in 26 archival boxes and about 13 linear feet of material. The NCRPE records date from 1971 to 1994, but there are many projects, programs and publications dealing with the relation between religion and public education before the NCRPE was founded. For example, there is a sampling of material in what was called "character education" in 1941, "moral and spiritual values" in the 1940s and 1950s, "released time" courses in biblical literature, "dual enrollment" or shared time, controversial issues such as tax support for non-public schools. In addition, there are the complete texts of U.S. Supreme Court decisions on released time, prayer and Bible reading in the public schools. Included are some of the conferences in the 1960s which sought to respond to the Supreme Court rulings. These materials came from the files of Richard U. Smith, the first NCRPE executive director.
This collection completes and supplements Record Group No 74, which covered the development of the Religious Education Association from 1903 to 1982 (although the call to the founding convention was issued in 1902) and record Group No 74-A, which brings the organization's records up to 2004 when it merged with the Association of Professors and Researchers in Religious Education. Record Groups 154 and 154-A cover the history of the APRRE from 1970 to 2004. Both the R.E.A. and APRRE were organizational members of the NCRPE. It is very appropriate that these archives are stored at Yale, since the R.E.A. had its headquarters on the campus of Yale Divinity School from 1973 to 1997, and the General Secretary of the R.E.A., Boardman Kathan, was an alumnus. It is important to point out that there is some overlap and repetition in the files. Many came from the Editors and the Presidents and have not been precisely separated by categories.
Arrangement
I. Early Developments
II. Pre-NCRPE Programs
III. History, Organization, and Policy
IV. Committees and Board of Directors
V. Secretarial Records and Correspondence
VI. Annual Meetings
VII. Publications
VIII. Foundations, Finances, and Membership
IX. Curriculum
X. Other Organizations
Religion in the public schools -- United States; National Council on Religion and Public Education (U.S.)
- Early Developments, Series I; Series I, Early Developments, contains a diverse collection of files and documents relating to programs dealing with religion and public education, many reflecting the life and career of Richard U. Smith in Michigan, Hawaii, and Montgomery County, Maryland. Of particular interest are materials in Character Education in Detroit, Michigan, Released Time classes in Flint, Michigan, and courses in the Bible as literature in Florida and Maryland. There is a substantial body of material dealing with the relationship between public and non-public schools in what was called "Dual Enrollment" or Shared Time, and programs on weekday religious education, including the "Through-The-Week" curriculum of the National Council of Churches in 1968-70.
  - Character Education, Flint, Michigan, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Released Time, Flint, Michigan, 1941-44 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bible Literature, Old Testament, Flint, Michigan, 1941-42 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bible Literature, New Testament, Flint, Michigan, 1941-42 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Moral and spiritual values, 1944-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Montgomery County, Maryland Public Schools, 1963-73 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bible as Literature, Broward County, Florida (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Resources for teaching the Bible (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Language Arts, Rockville, Maryland (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bible as Literature, Montgomery County, Maryland (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - U.S. Supreme Court, McCollum Case, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - U.S. Supreme Court, Zorach Case, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - U.S. Supreme Court, Engel v. Vitale, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - U.S. Supreme Court, Abington v. Schempp, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - U.S. Supreme Court decisions, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - U.S. Supreme Court, Walz v. NY Tax Commission, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - U.S. Supreme Court decisions, 1971, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
  - Articles about legal decisions (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Court decisions and policy (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Legal decisions (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Louis Cassels, UPI (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - New York State issues (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Protestant church statements (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Public funds for non-public schools (Box 4, Folder 26-27)
  - Religion in schools, general (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - School vouchers (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Tax support for parochial schools (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Teaching of values (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Columbia, Maryland Cooperative Ministry (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Weekday Religious Education conference, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Study conference for Weekday Religious Education, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Second National Conference on Weekday Religious Education, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Through-The-Week Curriculum, National Council of Churches, 1968-70 (Box 5, Folder 36-39)
  - Articles on Dual Enrollment, by Richard U. Smith, 1961-63; including views of the U.S. Government, Roman Catholic Church, Jewish, National Council of Churches (Protestant) (Box 6, Folder 40-49)
- Pre-NCRPE Programs, Series II; Series II, Pre-NCRPE Programs, includes several important conferences in the 1960s which led to the formation of the NCRPE. The National Conference of Christians and Jews, along with Harvard Divinity School and the School of Education, sponsored a conference on "Religion and Public Education" in 1966 in Cambridge, and the papers were published the next year in a book edited by Theodore R. Sizer, Dean of the School of Education. The NCCJ and the Connecticut Council of Churches put on a conference in Meriden in 1967 on "Teaching About Religion in the Public Schools." The Laymen's National Bible Committee ran a conference in 1969 at Wainwright House in Rye, NY on "The Bible in Public Schools." The Educational Communication Association held a conference in 1970 in Washington, DC, but that file is missing.
  - Moral and Spiritual Values: National Education Association, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Moral and Spiritual Education: National PTA, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Public Education and Freedom of Religion Conference, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Harvard University and NCCJ Conference and program, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews and Connecticut Council Churches, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - New York Values Education (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Religion and Social Studies, Florida State (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Religion in Social Studies, Pittsburgh (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Seabury House Consultation, Episcopal Church, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Religion in the Public Schools, American Association of School Administrators, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Wainwright House Conference, Laymen's National Bible Committee, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- History, Organization and Policy, Series III; Series III, History, Organization and Policy, features the organizational conference of the NCRPE, along with other files on Incorporation, By Laws, Distribution Center, and policy issues. The proceedings of the 1971 conference were published in Part 2, July-August 1972 issue of the journal, Religious Education.
  - Consultation and Organizational Conference, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - History of the NCRPE (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Incorporation as separate organization, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - NCRPE By Laws (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Distribution Center (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Iowa State application (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Job Description, Executive Director (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Equal Access Act (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Future of the Journal (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - End of the NCRPE (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Committees and Board of Directors, Series IV; Series IV, Committees and Board of Directors, has the minutes of the committees and the board, although the terms are sometimes used interchangeably. The Steering Committee existed from 1971 to 1973, when a Board of Directors was elected with an Executive Committee. However, in the early 1990s the Executive Committee was mistakenly called the Steering Committee. There is also a Futures Committee and one file for the Board.
  - Steering Committee, 1971-73 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee, 1973-1994 (Box 9, Folder 2-7)
  - Board of Directors (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Futures Committee (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Secretarial Records and Correspondence, Series V; Series V, Secretarial Records and Correspondence, includes the records of not only the Executive Directors, but also of the Presidents. The archival box on Correspondence is filed in chronological order.
  - Executive Directors
    - Richard U. Smith, 1971-75 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Daryl Adrian, 1975-79 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Walter Horlander, 1975-79 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Lynn Taylor, 1979-87 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Gerrit tenZythoff, 1987-88 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Chairmen/Presidents
    - Boardman Kathan, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Neil McCluskey, 1972-1975 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - J. Blaine Fister, 1975-1979 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - James Wood, 1979-1983 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Wes Bodin, 1983-1985 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Nicholas Piediscalzi, 1985-1988 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Charles Haynes, 1988-1992 (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
    - Austin Creel, 1992-1994 (Box 10, Folder 14-15)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1985-1989 (Box 11, Folder 16-20)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 11, Folder 21-25)
- Annual Meetings, Series VI; Series VI, Annual Meetings, provides and programs and notes of the NCRPE annual meetings from 1972 to 1994. In subsequent years, there were several such meetings or forums annually.
  - Chicago, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Columbus, Ohio, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Chicago, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Philadelphia, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Chicago, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - St. Louis, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - New York City, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Lawrence, Kansas, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Muncie, Ind., 1980 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Ames, Iowa, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
  - Springfield, MO, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Indianapolis, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Chicago, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Chicago, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - New York City, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Dallas, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Washington, DC, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Washington, DC, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Washington, DC, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Chevy Chase, MD, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Washington, DC, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Annual meetings [place not identified], 1993, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 23-24)
  - Forum, New York City, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 25)
- Publications, Series VII; Series VII, Publications, has copies of the NCRPE Bulletin from 1974 to 1983, and also copies of the journal, Religion and Public Education from 1984 to 1994; the journal is also catalogued among periodicals in the library. This series also contains many files of the editors, Don Wimmer, Thayer Warshaw and Charles Kniker, and associates, along with a number of related files of the editorial process and the editorial board. The most extensive correspondence was carried on by editors Warshaw and Kniker. There is also one small file of an attempted newsletter in the last years of the NCRPE.
  - NCRPE Bulletins, 1974-1978, 1979-1984 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - Bulletin finances (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
  - Bulletin subscriptions (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Bulletin survey, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Journal survey, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Journal book reviews (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, George Gilmore (Box 9)
  - Editor's annual reports (Box 15, Folder 10-11)
  - Editorial board (Box 15, Folder 12-14)
  - Editor proposal, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Future journal authors (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Assistant to the Editor (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Guest editors (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Journal authors (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Journal examination copies (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Charles Kniker, Journal editor (Box 16, Folder 21-23)
  - Journal review/survey (Box 16, Folder 24)
  - Journal reprints (Box 16, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper articles (Box 16, Folder 26)
  - News editor (Box 16, Folder 27)
  - NCRPE Newsletter (Box 16, Folder 28)
  - Journal testimonials (Box 16, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, Nicholas Piediscalzi (Box 16, Folder 30)
  - Journal form letter (Box 17, Folder 31)
  - Norma Thompson (Box 17, Folder 32)
  - Pamela Kennedy (Box 17, Folder 33)
  - Letter to U.S. Presidential candidates, 1987-88 (Box 17, Folder 34)
  - Questions and Answers, flyers (Box 17, Folder 35)
  - Religion and Higher Education (Box 17, Folder 36)
  - Survey of State laws (Box 17, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, Thayer Warshaw (Box 17, Folder 38-39)
  - Undergraduate research assistants (Box 17, Folder 40)
  - Warren Nord (Box 17, Folder 41)
  - Journal, Religion and Public Education, 1984-1988 (Box 18, Folder 42)
  - Journal, Religion and Public Education, 1988-1994 (Box 19, Folder 43)
- Foundations, Finances and Membership, Series VIII; Series VIII, Foundations, Finances and Membership, combines three somewhat related subjects, namely the sources of funding, the treasurer and financial reports, and membership and mailing lists.
  - NCRPE finances (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Final treasurer's report (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - John Donovan, treasurer (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Mailing list (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Memberships (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Promotions (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Treasurer (Box 20, Folder 7-8)
  - Finances, tax exemption (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - NCRPE finances, budget, bills, misc., 1986-95 (Box 21, Folder 10-14)
  - Foundations, incl. proposals (Box 21, Folder 15-16)
  - Stone Foundation (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - Lilly Endowment (Box 21, Folder 18-19)
- Curriculum, Series IX; Series IX, Curriculum, presents a sample of the different kinds of curriculum materials which were promoted and, in some cases, produced by the NCRPE.
  - Bible and Literature, Indiana University (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Indiana Religion Studies (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Linda Meixner (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Models for teacher education (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Religious Dimensions of World Culture (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Religion in the classroom (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Religion in Human Culture (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - World Religions, Ontario, Canada (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Religious Values (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - The Bible in Literature classes (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Pennsylvania Humanities (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Thinking and Rethinking U.S. History (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Genesis Project (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Values and Meaning project (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Values in the Classroom (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Wisconsin (Box 22, Folder 16)